in this video we are going to learn what
I think is one of the coolest design
patterns The Observer pattern once you
learn this pattern you are going to
notice it everywhere The Observer
pattern is from the behavioral category
if you don't know what that means check
the first video of this series where we
first introduce the concept of design
patterns and learn about their
categories The Observer pattern allows
us to observe to watch part of our
application and ensure that when one
part changes all the other parts that
depend on it can automatically update
themselves with the Observer pattern we
Define a subscription system where
various parts of our application can
subscribe to other parts just like how
you might subscribe to a newsletter when
something changes in the part you are
subscribed to the newsletter all
subscribers get notified about this
change automatically this way our
application components stay updated and
work together smoothly similar to how
your mailbox gets a new edition of of
the newsletter whenever there's
something new to share as we know the
category of Behavioral design patterns
is all about how elements communicate
with each other this is what this
pattern is for it's to share information
among different parts of an application
in an efficient and organized way the
Observer pattern has two ingredients
subjects and observers the subject is
the class we are interested on and The
Observers are the classes that are
watching the subject the cool thing
about this pattern is that many
different unrelated classes can be
observers let's imagine a music festival
in our Festival we have a band the
subject and we also have many observers
the fans the security the light and more
so we are going to first create an
interface that all observers no matter
how different they are are going to
implement for an element to become
Observer they need to have a method
called notify that will receive an event
argument of string type so all our
observers will implement it but they
will all behave in a deep different way
the fan will receive the event if the
event is start they will say yay if the
event is end they will say thanks bye
the security also received the event if
the event is a start they will close the
door when the event is end they will
open the door the light also received
the event they only care about the play
song event when they receive this event
they will shine as you can see they are
all different but they all implement the
same method in their own way so now that
we have The Observers let's implement
the band the subject just like anything
can be an observer as long as it
implements The Observer interface
anything can be a subject as long as it
implements the subject interface the
subject interface will need to have
three methods one to add an observer one
to remove an observer and another one to
notify The Observers of a change on the
implementation on the band class we are
going to keep the observers on an
observer array the add Observer method
will add an observer to the array the
remove of server method will remove the
Observer from the array and then notify
observers will go through the array and
call the notify method of each one of
The Observers remember all the observers
have a notified method here all we are
doing is calling that method with an
event then our band class will call its
methods when the concert starts we will
notify The Observers with the start
event and we will also notify The
Observers with Play song and end concert
recap all we are doing is creating
Observer classes these classes have a
notified method then we are creating a
subject class and we are giving all The
Observers to it the subject class will
then call the notify method of each one
of The Observers to run this code we
first create The Observers we initialize
the band and we add The Observers to the
band then when the concert starts when
the song is playing or when the concert
ends all our observers will get notified
how cool is this we now have a system
and wear a band and its fans security
and lights are all able to do their own
thing separately but they remain in sync
through the Subscribe and notify
mechanism that's why the Observer
pattern is so cool the parts of our
system can now share information in a
clean and flexible way maybe I'm a nerd
but I find this so cool that's it for
this video if you found it helpful
please click the like And subscribe
button this is the third video I make on
design pattern if you would like me to
keep going then write it down on the
comments below or maybe we can change
topics and talk about the data
structures and algorithms for a bit you
tell me write your opinion down in the
comments I'm gonna be looking at them
right now if you like the way I explain
things and you would like to learn
things like JavaScript python react
react native gold Dart flutter among
many many others for absolutely free all
you have to do is click the link below
to join any of our many free courses
that you can take right now for
absolutely free with me click the link
below and I will see you there anjana
comes see you on the next one
bye